Govind Das: Okay, you can rename it, rename it.
Govind Das: Correct.
Govind Das: Cardia, cardio.
Govind Das: Okay, okay.
Govind Das: Thank you, thank you.
Govind Das: Audio checking. Got it.
Govind Das: I don't lose it, though.
Govind Das: The pyramid will cause.
Govind Das: New zone?
Govind Das: Nothing with that.
Govind Das: Karan, you're able to hear me?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Ruji?
Govind Das: Lib?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Clear, clear. Good.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Should we begin, or should we… we'll wait for some participant?
Govind Das: We can… we can summarize, and we can continue, because respect those who've come one time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, namaste, everyone, and I welcome you to the day 3 of… Our 5-day training.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I hope all of you have kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, the two exercises I had shared kind of builds up today's workshop. So today's day is built on those exercises. So, any… anyone would like to share, or maybe
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any difficulty encountered during those exercises before, before we dive in here?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Okay. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, last time, we were trying to see the current Chattushte of Vedanta, how the rishis have conceptualized minds, and today we'll be building on that concept and kind of move further in sandskadas and vasnas and…
Dr. Karan Mittal: other aspects of, other aspects of index psychology. So, before we get there, Boom.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Roger. I think…
Govind Das: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This will kind of summarize the whole… Last year, last names, yeah.
Govind Das: So, the modern fragmented view… Sees things from the box perspective.
Govind Das: Manas, Buddhi, ahankar, the concept of Chitta is not there.
Govind Das: Alright?
Govind Das: The explanation is also very specialized.
Govind Das: At the same time, very isolated.
Govind Das: Explanation is isolated, even the application is isolated.
Govind Das: Of course, Some people do try to integrate.
Govind Das: But the Bharati Darshana, except for Sankhya, in regards to explanation, It is all integrated.
Govind Das: In the Bhagavatam, we mentioned.
Govind Das: that how do you know what is Buddhi? How do you know what is Manas? How do you know what is Ahankara? How do you know?
Govind Das: What is Chitta?
Govind Das: It can only be known by its function.
Govind Das: Right? When you are feeling, that is mind.
Govind Das: When you're analyzing, that is Guddhi.
Govind Das: When you are angry, I will show them that is your iHu.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: And where do they spring from? They all spring from this top, which is called a chitta.
Govind Das: the Sanskaras. It is called as sanskaras.
Govind Das: Right? The impressions… Which are there since our many, many past conditioning. The past conditioning
Govind Das: Not necessarily from the past life, certainly from the past life also.
Govind Das: But the past conditioning also means our Present past, our childhood conditioning.
Govind Das: Right? And that conditioning, for example, one person, Was telling me, that…
Govind Das: When she came to her in-law's house, With a new baby.
Govind Das: Living in some other country, when she came to her in-law's house.
Govind Das: There was a preconceived impression about dealing with the mother-in-law.
Govind Das: And because of the preconditioning of dealing with the mother-in-law, the breast milk was not flowing.
Govind Das: Here's a true example.
Govind Das: And simply by the change of place, when she came to her mother's place, which was fortunately just
Govind Das: 5-7 kilometer. Naturally, the milk was flowing.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: It was not some black magic, it was not anatomical problem, it was not neurological problem. Yes, there was an impact on neurological problem, but it was based upon past impressions.
Govind Das: Alright? So, therefore, the beauty of Baharati Darshanaha.
Govind Das: It does not talk only the past.
Govind Das: It does not talk about the deeper past of the past life.
Govind Das: It does talk about it so that it can deal with the present one.
Govind Das: So, therefore, the mind, Bhutti, Hankara, when they're integrated properly.
Govind Das: with the principle of yoga. Yoga is the process of unwinding our conditioning.
Govind Das: The word yoga means Dharma plus kriya is equal to yoga.
Govind Das: According to, again, the Bhagavatam Third Kanto, Dharma means
Govind Das: universal law plus yoga, when they're integrated, it gives rise to yoga. Kriya.
Govind Das: So, therefore, the Ayurveda the Bhagavad Gita.
Govind Das: They do explain these things separately.
Govind Das: But the application for healing.
Govind Das: And functioning of these 3-4 principles, Buddha, Ahankara, Manasa, and Chitta, will always remain integrated. Another simple example.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: When the child is restless, now nobody knows why the child is restless.
Govind Das: Child is angry, nobody knows why the child is restless or angry.
Govind Das: So, Ayurveda does talk about giving some soft… cow butter, with some… Candy sugar. Kadi Shakkar.
Govind Das: And applying little aisle on the head, coconut oil.
Govind Das: What happens?
Govind Das: The child is specified.
Govind Das: One may say, Bhatto, they did not deal with the mind, they did not deal with the putti, they did not deal with the Ankara.
Govind Das: We've got childhood… Is only giving responses
Govind Das: But the child cannot analyze. Therefore, the best thing is, through simple method of Annamay kosh, All the…
Govind Das: Bhutti kosher, ahankar kosher, mana kosher is specified.
Govind Das: And it can also apply to the adults also.
Govind Das: Yep.
Govind Das: Yes, Karan?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. So, last time we could not cover the Anthakaran Chattusha properly, and today I would like to kind of go deeper into the concept and kind of also give… share a few examples of how this concept works. So, we all know that Anthakaran is divided into four faculties, what we saw last time. So, first, probably, is Manas.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And Manus is basically, you know, the whole…
Dr. Karan Mittal: whole impulsive mind, which kind of compares the likes, the dislikes, option A, option B, gets attracted to things, gets repulsive to things. So Manas is basically that monkey mind, what we call about, which has… which takes data, which kind of weighs the data, so that part lies with Manas.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Buddhi is the discriminative one. It's that intelligent, the frontal part of the brain that kind of makes the decision based on prior experiences, based on data, based on advices, based on judgment. So different, different
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, kind of parameters Buddhi takes into account while making that decision. That's why Buddhi is that Vivek. So, it's called as Nishayat Mika Bhutti. One who makes the decision is the Buddhi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ahankara is that I miss how much I associate myself into the problem. For example.
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably if someone just, you know, like in my family is probably creating a chaos, then I get affected by that chaos, because I have my highness associated with that family member.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if a friend's family member is probably making a chaos, I might feel for that friend, but I will not, you know, get disturbed as much as I get disturbed. So, how much you associate
Dr. Karan Mittal: yourself to a problem decides how much you get disturbed by it. I know people who get disturbed by, you know, geopolitical issues.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, you know, religious issues, etc. Because they have their kindness kind of entangled into the whole thing. So, it's not right or wrong. When we deal with antikar and Chattushte, it's not right or wrong. But what is serving the client and what's not serving the client is, as counselors, are part to judge and kind of decide.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then Chitta is basically
Dr. Karan Mittal: the past impressions, and the past impressions in Indian, like, when we see from an Indic perspective, it's not just this life, it kind of spans across lifetimes, and even, like, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In psychology, there was a debate called as a nurture versus nature debate. Nature people said that you have inner traits that kind of determine the whole life of yours, that is the genetics or whatever.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the nurture was how you kind of bring up a child will determine his whole life. So, IKS, or our rishis never segregated tools. We didn't have those black and white perspectives, okay? We said nature is also important, and also nurturing Vaigyana and Vagyana is equally important, and both go hand in hand.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, chitta is basically the storehouse of your deeper memories, your likings. Sometimes you don't have an explanation for a particular like or a dislike. That is basically the chitta acting. So it could be this life, childhood, it could be some past life, your experiences, what all gets stored in Chitta. Now, as rishis have propagated.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we don't see these faculties as separate, okay? We kind of combine these faculties and see the client as a whole. And every problem that comes to us, there's an intervention on all these faculties, like Rubji said, that
Dr. Karan Mittal: even that application of oil and taking that, you know, khdi Shakkar and all that stuff, it's… it's how you target the underme kosher to give an effect into the Manome kosher. That will be done on the day 5. But even if I see from the underkaran perspective, so, like, suppose I'll give you an example. I have a client
Dr. Karan Mittal: a couple who's coming to me for sessions, couples counseling. Now, I'm just speaking about the wife. Now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do I analyze, from an IKIS perspective, the case? So now the wife has a chitta which talks about perfection. Her father has conditioned her to have everything in life at a perfection level.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, for the husband, she'll kind of keep on correcting the husband, etc. So, the Chitta is overpowering the Manasseen Buddhi because of a past sunscar.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, if I go from a Buddhi problem, then she doesn't have a priority set.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How much importance to give the food the husband eats, to the clothes does when…
Dr. Karan Mittal: wares to the relationship, all that is not prioritized. So everything is entangled and enmeshed within each other, and smaller things then take priority in her because of her Buddhi issues. So what we do is, first, working on the father's conditioning of perfection, that everything in your life cannot be perfect, okay, though you strive for it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Buddhi, we set her… we teach her priorities of, you know, what to give importance and what to neglect.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, also, if the relationship is not right, she has her ego because of the Chitta thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: of perfection, because the relationship is not right, I'm doing something wrong, how can that be with me? So our ego gets entangled with the problem, so we have to detach that also, that your relationship being smooth or
Dr. Karan Mittal: difficult or rough is not what you are, so we have to, you know, kind of detangle that part also. So, how you analyze a particular case on these four things, and then target everything accordingly? Like, another case that I have is about mobile addiction, a social media influencer.
Dr. Karan Mittal: completely addicted to mobile, 7 hours, 6 hours, checking reels, comments, etc, etc. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, the social media, I cannot tell him to stop social media, okay? So, I started digging in, and what we found is the fame that he receives from social media attention, or the comments and likes, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is kind of, you know, fueling his self-worth, which has been a problem because of his father in childhood, okay? So father was absent, and he had to… he had some issues in childhood. So this fame that he's getting in social media makes him feel good about himself. So I had to detangle that part, that
Dr. Karan Mittal: You are not just how many comments, likes you get, you yourself have other capabilities and your profession, etc, which makes you who you are, not just the social media likes, dislikes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, then we go into the issues at home. So, wife, they also have couple issues, so… so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: wife has… things are not good with wife, so… because he wants to avoid talking with the wife. So, he gets more into the mobile and social media. So, how do we kind of analyze the same issue from different, different layers of the Antakarana
Dr. Karan Mittal: the other koshas that we'll discuss. And, you know, do targeted approaches for every perspective is what is the IK psychology. We don't see the person as behavior, mind, emotions, etc, etc, in target one. We see the person made up of many components, and then target each component in its own right. So that's about how we work with Antakaran Chattusha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Rosie.
Govind Das: Yes.
Govind Das: So, based on this Anthakarana Chitta.
Govind Das: Right, as we were mentioning, Chitta is nothing but the storehouse of our past condition.
Govind Das: The present past and the past past.
Govind Das: One may debate about the past life, but one cannot debate about the impressions.
Govind Das: Right? Impression nobody can debate.
Govind Das: So, therefore, based upon this, the… the one good thing
Govind Das: about the Western world, using the language.
Govind Das: Right.
Govind Das: Same, this sanskaras, this chitta, they created a concept called as cognitive bias.
Govind Das: Now, the language makes so much of sense, right? One of the… one of the limitations of the Bharatiya, which are vara.
Govind Das: We have not able to translate in the language where the modern people can understand.
Govind Das: So the same concept, the chitta, has been translated. So, these two friends.
Govind Das: No, they showed human judgment systematically deviates from probability.
Govind Das: What is the first system? Fast, automatic, effect-laden biases live here.
Govind Das: Second means slow, effortful, lazy by default. That means they take time. Lazy here not means wrong. They're not reactive.
Govind Das: So this Kenman and Traversky spoke about
Govind Das: this cognitive bias, we will try to see them where the language, because people are speaking in English.
Govind Das: So they were able to present very systematically the same concept of chitta. Once you learn that in English, then you can… unfortunately, you can reconnect to the concept of chitta.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I would just like to add over here, so for as a counselor, because I come from counseling background, how it is important, how this concept, what Kahneman and Torski suggested, actually, the concept is a concept from economics, but how it applies in psychology. Because we are counselors.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We also have these two sides of our brain. One is that is fast, automatic, and tries to fit things into particular, you know, compartments that we have in our brain.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the other part is naturally the slow one that thinks, that contemplates, etc. What happens is when clients approach us, if I know A to Z, or maybe A to H, I will try to fit that client into A2H because of the fast component.
Dr. Karan Mittal: My brain will naturally avoid the system too that is slow, contemplates on every single issue that the client has, and then probably derive a framework or a formulation.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But System 1 is the naturally active one in all of us. And once you fit that client into that particular thing, then all your therapy, diagnosis, etc. will just work according to that
Dr. Karan Mittal: framework that you have designed in System 1. So for us, it's very important to stay in System 2 when you are taking a session. Otherwise, because of your own biases, and because of your natural propensity of the brain to put that client into one of the boxes, you kind of deviate the third way, and that's why supervisions become research.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Rich.
Govind Das: Nope.
Govind Das: So, the store-offs of every impression.
Govind Das: Therefore, again, you know, the Bhartya, which are dara, whether yoga sutras, Or are you remaining?
Govind Das: for that matter, Puranas, the medical science.
Govind Das: Everyone believed in the concept of past life.
Govind Das: Punarjanma.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: Now, one may not be able to prove the existence of past life.
Govind Das: But one cannot disprove the concept of impressions.
Govind Das: Alright, therefore the chitta, the concept of chitta.
Govind Das: It's synonymous to cognitive bias going deeper.
Govind Das: Unfortunately, in the modern Ayurvedic School, they do not teach the concept of past.
Govind Das: They treat only based upon the symptom of the patient, the Roga.
Govind Das: And therefore, it becomes less impactful because
Govind Das: The whole system is rooted on the Chitta.
Govind Das: So, therefore, what happens? Chitta…
Govind Das: without Buddhi, like, the first one, what Kenman says about the first method, when Chitta is speaking through Manas without Buddhi getting awarded, immediate response.
Govind Das: Immediate reaction, like a small baby.
Govind Das: Right? We can see a small child. Totally…
Govind Das: Impress or totally obsessed with the mind.
Govind Das: The children only feel. They do not process.
Govind Das: And what is that? The Manasar… is…
Govind Das: impacted through Chitta without Buddhi being involved.
Govind Das: Therefore, cognitive bias is not a bug.
Govind Das: It is not something problem.
Govind Das: It is part of the consciousness, or chitta.
Govind Das: exhibited through the mind, and when Buddhi is applied there, Critical thinking is applied there.
Govind Das: Then what does it do? It has the power to balance.
Govind Das: Therefore, cognitive bias is not a bug. It is a samskara doing its own job.
Govind Das: And unfortunately, what we see today's generation, we make decisions based upon feeling.
Govind Das: What is it? When we make decisions based upon feeling, it is fully the samskaras being operated on.
Govind Das: We do not make decisions based upon facts. Fake feelings have value.
Govind Das: But we have to understand feelings are driven by the… chit thought.
Govind Das: Not a good thing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we'll do an exercise. Of course, we'll open the breakout rooms, but I'll just explain the exercise so there's no confusion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Suppose…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Maybe, maybe we, we can take up, like, both of you, like, we'll be working in pairs, and, you know, you can take up any experience that you had with a family member, or if you're a spiritual counselor, with your counselee, etc, where you have reacted, or spoken, or, you know, kind of opined faster than, you know, expected.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And we stay with that few seconds of your experience. It could be something that has happened very recently. So you can just stay with, you know, that few seconds of experience.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, probably, the therapist who's acting as a therapist will try to dig in that why did you do that? Okay? And then, probably, like we did last time, we try to do what, where, when, how. And once you get these answers, then probably then you need to understand where did that belief, or where did that sanskara start happening.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And if, supposedly, that Sanskara was not there.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what would have changed, okay? If you had given some more time before reacting.
Dr. Karan Mittal: would your response, or the way you analyze the situation change? For example, I'll give my example. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So usually I have this tendency of when a person is asking a question, or when I'm speaking on the phone, I reply very quickly, okay? I reply before, even before they complete.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So when… and as a therapist, it's a big flaw, because the client feels that you're not listening to them, okay, or you are, probably, there are many things, not listening to them, assuming things, or they don't feel that they are heard.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when I started working on that tendency of mine, even now you might notice that I speak very fast. So, when… when they started… when I started working on this tendency of mine.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, that how, when, where, why, all that exists. But then I understood that as a child, I was told that I need to be fast at doing things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, so I had to report to some, some, some, you know, senior of mine as a child, like a family member, of course, I cannot give the whole details. So, they used to say, Jaldi boh, Jaldi boh, just completed fast, we don't have that much time. So, as a child, I was kind of conditioned to act or speak faster than
Dr. Karan Mittal: what my thought process is then. And that is kind of affecting the way I interact with things. So don't take something very intense, take something that is, you know, probably something that you have noticed quite often, and it's a bit superficial, so that the therapist also who's acting as a therapist gets that bandwidth to practice with you, and vice versa.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, what would be have said if I had waited 30 seconds? So now, as a practice, what I do is, whenever someone is speaking, I have given myself a buffer of 5 seconds, that if the person is silent for 5 seconds, then I start sharing my thoughts. It helps the client
Dr. Karan Mittal: feeling that I'm hearing them. It also gives me that extra 5 seconds to kind of gather my thoughts, and then I speak. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, if I give that 5 minutes or 5 seconds of buffer, then of course the analysis changes, the diagnosis changes, the way I word things changes. So, this is the practice. Of course, I just said my experience, but this is how you do or do it in the pair. Any doubt about the practice?
Aarti Ganesh: Could you elaborate the second point? Like, whose voice does the assumption sound like?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, so the second point is, like, once you reach with what, where, when, why, how, then you have to, kind of think that where did it start?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so for me, it started with that senior family member who said, that is that senior family member. Sometimes it could be a teacher, you are dirty at doing things, be very clean, or your notes, your handwriting is very shabby, so start being organized. So, whose voice in your head kind of associates itself with that particular belief of yours?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So, I think that will evolve. When did it start, or who started that belief for you? I think that will evolve as you know that exist, right?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so I'll just start the breakout rooms. Of course, and Prabhuji will be hopping into rooms like last time. So, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Till then, you can just think about…
Dr. Karan Mittal: What, sanskara you want to, or what habit you want to catch.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Oops.
Dr. Karan Mittal: 10 minutes? Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Wuji.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think everyone is assigned.
Govind Das: Mingo.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: Everything, you know, anymore.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Karuna.
18D110012_Suraj Sahadev Racha: Citizen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Just in general.
Govind Das: She's not genuine lah.
Govind Das: Neha Gokul is not there, Nina.
Dr. Karan Mittal: She's not done any visitors.
Sneha G: Rabhuji, can I just stay in somewhere and listen? I'm basically on the road right now.
Govind Das: Can I save it?
Sneha G: Yeah, thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I'll just assign information.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, no.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ticket number, Z.
Govind Das: It's…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: or you will do it yourself, whenever you need to.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry?
Govind Das: I don't join on my…
Dr. Karan Mittal: How you joining? Okay. Take care.
Sree Mallipeddi: Hello?
Sree Mallipeddi: Yeah, yeah.
Sneha G: Hi, Krishna, I need to join Breakout Room 5, can you help?
Sattvastha Ventures: I will assign you… It was Nehaji, but, just…
Sneha G: Yes, I was in breakout room 5, but I got disconnected.
Sattvastha Ventures: Oh, okay, you were assigned already. Okay, I will… I will help you with it.
Sneha G: Yes, it was 5, I think, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry, it took some time to help a few participants.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that was the exercise about Sunstaras. I think many of you could figure it out, how to take the client. Even at this level, going one or two more steps deeper is more than enough. You cannot go right to the core and change the memory. But just, you know, sometimes
Dr. Karan Mittal: Once the mind understands that the origin of this memory is my father.
Dr. Karan Mittal: who had that ego of, you know, probably doing things immediately, and doing things right, and always being the perfectionist, mind starts contemplating that whether it's right for me or not. And automatically, that ripple effect starts changing a few of samskada. Sometimes just knowing the belief, the subconscious takes over and starts changing it. For now, that's the exercise. We'll push it further later.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Rich.
Govind Das: It's, again, there are… This life, the childhood conditioning, are very, very powerful. Again, last time we were discussing.
Govind Das: the information You know, when you'll get proper information as you're growing.
Govind Das: The knowledge is always subservient to the conditioning.
Govind Das: to undo conditioning, just like if you are a South Indian.
Govind Das: Pure South Indian being raised in Tamil Nadu, Andhra Pradesh.
Govind Das: when that time, you eat dhi rice, but if you come to Punjab, your Dhi Parotas.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: And the girl is married to Punjabi, living in Punjab.
Govind Das: However good she is, Alright, want to adjust herself.
Govind Das: But her conditioning, what does it do? It causes such a inconvenience to her.
Govind Das: Right? It takes longer time, so therefore, One is the Buddhi.
Govind Das: which will process… And then reconditioning of ourself.
Govind Das: And therefore, in the Gurukul system, more than knowledge, they were conditioned.
Govind Das: To a certain lifestyle.
Govind Das: And once you are conditioned to certain lifestyle, that becomes your bootti, that becomes your personality.
Govind Das: Alright, so therefore, this life…
Govind Das: After the childhood comes modern environmental loading. Even if you're studying nights, I remember one boy.
Govind Das: He went to extremely good Gurukul, where the Sanskrit was at the forefront.
Govind Das: Living in a smaller village.
Govind Das: But some other within that village, he came in touch with some people who were in the movie industry.
Govind Das: Next time I see him in Mumbai, writing script for the movies.
Govind Das: Imagine, you know, there was such a shift off.
Govind Das: Cultural conditioning, so the childhood conditioning
Govind Das: Was undone by the modern environmental loading.
Govind Das: You know, the dopamine economic…
Govind Das: And some scarves are now being installed at an industrial scale. Very important to understand.
Govind Das: And the past life, karmic carry.
Govind Das: You know, the past lab, again, I said, no need to debate about this. I don't believe in past life.
Govind Das: We can always say, you may not believe in past life, but you can always believe.
Govind Das: In the biological evolution.
Govind Das: Which is accepted by the modern scientists also.
Govind Das: Right. So therefore, those patterns which are there beyond our direct access to the childhood life.
Govind Das: Then, the… after the child, the modern environmental loading.
Govind Das: And imagine the past life karmic conditioning. These are the three layers of conditioning where everybody goes through.
Govind Das: experiencing chitta without Buddhi directly being involved. We'll deal this question of Buddhi later. Yes, Karl?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so just adding an example, Bruji, that, you know, it seems that these Sanskaras, how they hold true. So, I think I and Rajuji were dealing a case of couples counseling.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, you know, the Manas and the buddhi of the husband already knows that separation is needed, okay? But the sanskara, that there has been no divorce in our family.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay?
Dr. Karan Mittal: has… is so strong that Manas, Buddhi, and Ahanka are choosing to ignore everything, like, you know, the… because of the sansara, everything else is being ignored.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and the sanskara is taking over. In fact, Prabhuji was sharing that one of the very close relatives of that particular husband has undergone a divorce. But the Buddhi is trying to even, you know, ignore that reality, because that sanskara, that statement, ke, the family mehi kabi divorce nahi wine, is so very strong, right, Roji? So, sanskara's…
Dr. Karan Mittal: are not something that, you know, you'll find are very light or very, very, gentle. They can be as strong that they can kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: suppress the Buddhi, Manasa, and Hankar altogether.
Govind Das: And therefore, therefore, when, when, when he said that, Hamar, in our life, it has never happened, it is not that we immediately, oh, he's lying, I know it.
Govind Das: Yes, the lie is not lie, that lie is the thing but the strong conditioning of not accepting divorce, to such an extent.
Govind Das: Like, if you study these Shastras.
Govind Das: Right? Now, the cultural conditioning is that
Govind Das: In Hindu, Sanskriti, divorce is not there at all.
Govind Das: Divorce is a modern thing.
Govind Das: Alright? We make such statement.
Govind Das: But if you study carefully Manu Samhita.
Govind Das: In Manusamita, which is seen as extremely rigid text in regards to women.
Govind Das: There is a description of separation.
Govind Das: In Naradha Grajaya Sutra, there is a description. Dr. Radha Krishna Tripati, in his book, Wada, he gives…
Govind Das: he gives this explanation. In the 12th century, right, there were isolated incidents
Govind Das: Having very clear idea why they should separate.
Govind Das: But what does it do? The strong cultural condition has the power to…
Govind Das: You know, not to bring out those ideas in the forefront, because they believe the society will be destroyed.
Govind Das: So that is the power of conditioning of
Govind Das: Whatever happens, hell or high water, they should stay in this relationship.
Govind Das: Because the whole concept of marriage is so…
Govind Das: you know, so much there is a rigidity from the traditional point of view, and now there is a rigidity in regards to liberal point of view. Therefore, I took this example.
Govind Das: Yup.
Govind Das: Yeah.
Govind Das: So, therefore, Some patterns in you are older than your memory of them, and they're still workable.
Govind Das: Right.
Govind Das: Some patterns in you are older than your memory of them. Kosmaranne Yoga.
Govind Das: You may not recollect them, but they are there in the subconscious mind.
Govind Das: They comment here and there, therefore, what is it?
Govind Das: Again, I don't want to debate. I believe in Punarjanma. I'm a student of Gita.
Govind Das: But still, as a psychology… learning…
Govind Das: We are talking, rather than debating about Punarjanma, we can always accept the impression of the past.
Govind Das: whether the childhood passed or beyond that. Can you explain this epigenic?
Govind Das: Pardon?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so… so what happens is, like, when we do regression, etc. also, you know, there are some clients who don't believe in past lives, and there are some clients who believe in past lives.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Our… our role over here is not to support a narrative. Our role here is to understand that the Sanskara
Dr. Karan Mittal: can not always be explained. Now, if it's a believer client, then karma, punrajanma, past life, etc. becomes a good tool to kind of create hope and, you know, create some sense of relief in the client. But if the client is not
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, kind of believing in it, then you don't, you know, kind of impose the Punar Jammu rebirth concept, because I don't know, every one of you works with different kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: clients. So, we get clients from different regions and faith also, so we don't try to impose it. But then, there are other explanations also that why this particular cultural belief has come in, and Jung has also spoken about, you know, collective unconscious, and how different, different beliefs come from the society, culture, the mankind as a whole. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we try to work on the sanskara itself. We don't kind of put the label of past life, etc, etc, but it's… from an IKS perspective, it's very important to work on that particular sanskara of that person. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The reason could be anything. You can define it from genetics, you can define it from Punarjanma, karma theory, astronomogy, etc, etc, but being aware of the Sanskara and working on it is what Arishis described.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it also kind of gives us
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, when someone believes in this theory of Panas Jammu, past lives, or rebirths, etc, it gives more… more space for things to expand, for some things to kind of, be, some things get settled because of the karma theory, some things get settled because of the Jammu theory. So, from a Hindu or IKS perspective, sometimes it acts as a good tool, but we don't impose that on our clients.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah? Sometimes in spiritual counseling, we try to impose it too much, but that doesn't give respite to the client. It, in fact, increases the pain sometimes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this is one of the most important statements, and that's why self-work is important. The therapist's unconscious is always in the room.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whether the client's conscious or you're conscious, whether the therapist's conscious is there in the room, we don't know. But the therapist's unconscious. You are always… when you're sitting in that room, you are always kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: judging, seeing, saying things based on your unconscious. And that's why self-worth becomes so important, so that you don't judge a client based on your unconscious and subconscious impressions. Therapy is not about sitting in a pedestal and just speaking it up. It's also working on your impressions and your unconscious.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, we should move.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we'll come to a few biases.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And, of course, we'll… because it's more of a bias concept, we'll not go very deep, but… but how these biases affect us. Like, confirmation biases.
Dr. Karan Mittal: something that you have already believed in your mind to exist, and you start imposing that. It happens a lot with, you know, relationship counseling. Suppose I see the wife first in my counseling session, and wife creates a narrative about the husband.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the session… probably the husband joins therapy a few sessions later. I will be seeing the husband from the perspective the wife has created in me.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, what is very important is, like, suppose someone is referring you a client, and he says that this guy, your problem is, this is this client's problem, etc, etc. And you kind of take in that narrative and kind of imbibe it within yourself, and when that client or the counselor comes to you, you will be just
Dr. Karan Mittal: Working from that narrative and seeing those small, smaller things that confirm that narrative within you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So it's very important that, you know, in therapy also, what I do many times is, suppose a client is taking therapy for a few sessions, there's a gap of two, three weeks, and then traveling or some family function, and the client resumes in the fourth week. The new session… the fourth… the session that's happening in the fourth week, for me as a therapist, is a new session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I keep all the past data separate, I again ask the client what's happening, what are the issues, for a few minutes, so that I get new data, and I just don't work on the confirmation that I did in session one, and continue it further. So it's very important to become that empty container, and every time try to fill in the new information that you're getting. So that's confirmation bias.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the antidote I've just written, you kind of gather also those
Dr. Karan Mittal: Traits of the client that disconfirm your analysis and diagnosis, and then decide for yourself which part holds strong.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Rebuji.
Govind Das: Cultural bias. One of the students was mentioning in the discussion.
Govind Das: About, how she was…
Govind Das: Consciously reminded how she should be here because she's a girl.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: So, what happens? The cultural bias is built from the childhood.
Govind Das: It is made to be normal.
Govind Das: Alright, if the sun is born, you celebrate If daughter is gone.
Govind Das: You celebrate after a little time. You take some time, oh, right, what is it? This cultural bias connected to gender, this cultural bias connected to
Govind Das: the… You know, the upper class, lower class, the cultural bias connected to food habits, right?
Govind Das: Like, the… just because somebody does not drink They're not necessarily moralist.
Govind Das: And just because somebody drinks.
Govind Das: That one quality does not make us define, oh, he's a spoiled person, right? But this cultural bias, what do they do? They're extremely strong in identifying people as criminals.
Govind Das: Right.
Govind Das: So, therefore, it is very important
Govind Das: To deal with this cultural bias, In a way.
Govind Das: applying more Buddhi. Therefore, if you see, even the religion.
Govind Das: You know, the disadvantage of religious bias.
Govind Das: I would add that also in the cultural bias.
Govind Das: Is that the religious people can be extremely judgmental.
Govind Das: In regards to those who are not practicing their religion.
Govind Das: In regards to practicing their own religion, and not as much as they are practicing.
Govind Das: So what does it do? That bias creates a superiority complex.
Govind Das: You know? And therefore, When something in the client's life feels obviously wrong or right.
Govind Das: And cultural bias, one of the problems of cultural bias, it operates on the principle of right and wrong.
Govind Das: For example, one more example, I'll say that Karin can take it forward. You know, somebody eats meat.
Govind Das: Oh, how can they do it?
Govind Das: Immediately.
Govind Das: The bias comes there, and they are seen as sinful, they are seen as local, they are seen as untouchable.
Govind Das: Right? Even though scripture is more evolving in regards to being from a non-vegetarian to vegetarian, they are not contradictory concepts.
Govind Das: Their evolving concept. That is a different way to look.
Govind Das: Yes, sir.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Christian.
Dr. Karan Mittal: modules.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so… so, cultural and moral bias, also, if you're into the spiritual counseling realm, these are the biases that take over a lot, okay? If you decide that if a person is not doing a particular spiritual practice, then he's good for nothing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And suppose a client comes to you and shares this issue, etc. Somewhere or the other, unconsciously, subconsciously, you are creating a belief that he's not serious on the spiritual saddler, and that's why he has this problem, etc. So, cultural bias is not just about the childhood experiences, etc. It's also, if you belong to a particular culture, cult, sect, how much of those beliefs do you try to impose on the other client? And that happens very common. Sometimes we don't
Dr. Karan Mittal: Don't even realize that we're doing that.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, someone is not wearing clothes of a particular way, someone is, someone coming from LGBTQ community, live in relationships. These are the things where you have to be really careful, because
Dr. Karan Mittal: Somewhere or the other, your thinking will change, and the way you present the issue or the solutions to the client will also change. Like, for example, Onresh also, you will subconsciously start
Dr. Karan Mittal: judging the client and trying to impose that a vegetarian lifestyle is better. And then you will kind of give reasons to your brain, okay, it reduces the Rajas Guna, it will reduce the aggressiveness, it will reduce the acidity problem, it will do this, it will do that. But it's not these things that you have… you're scanning the client for. You are
Dr. Karan Mittal: working from your bias. So it's very good… important to contemplate that why are you suggesting what you are suggesting.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And moral bias, as we all know, that it's about what's right and wrong. So, LGBTQ and all these things nowadays… Probhji, would you like to add to moral bias? Yeah.
Govind Das: Yeah, again, moral bias is, again, based upon the cultural bias, we create certain, you know, assumed morality. There are universal laws.
Govind Das: Right? Dharma deals with universal laws.
Govind Das: And the morality is also sometimes man-made.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: So in the man-made laws, when they contradict with the universal law, here we focus more on right and wrong.
Govind Das: The universal laws do not focus on right and wrong. Universal laws focus on action and consequences.
Govind Das: if you study how Jatayu spoke to Ravan, It's very interesting.
Govind Das: Jetayu spoke to Ravan from the principle of action and consequences.
Govind Das: He said, you are a king.
Govind Das: People will follow your behavior.
Govind Das: Jatay, you said, you know what, you should only carry the burden as much as you can handle.
Govind Das: So this is very important if you're a therapist with high moral value, which is very important.
Govind Das: But then what does it do? It makes such people unforgivable for even small, slight infringement, because they operate from the principle of
Govind Das: right and wrong.
Govind Das: But the universal morality operates on the principle of Action and consequences.
Govind Das: Big difference between the two.
Govind Das: Right? When you, when you narrate the concept based upon action and consequences.
Govind Das: Then you are giving them the space to think.
Govind Das: But when we are doing based upon right and wrong.
Govind Das: Either they completely submit and not have a conversation.
Govind Das: Or they rebel against and choose their own path.
Govind Das: Correct.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the diagnostic bias, of course, it doesn't… if you're into spiritual counseling, or parenting, or,
Dr. Karan Mittal: education field, it doesn't hold, too much of importance, but it's also, like, the modern psychology is also kind of, you know, debating on this. How important are labels to be put to the client? Anxiety kahe. How important are labels, and are those labels going to
Dr. Karan Mittal: benefit the client, or it will just become a label and a taboo and kind of stick to him for life. So, it doesn't hold too much of importance if you're into general counseling, but as therapists, we always try to kind of not
Dr. Karan Mittal: diagnose the client with a borderline personality disorder, depression, etc. We work around it, we have that framework within ourselves, but we don't… if the client has just come to the therapist and psychiatrist, etc, is not involved, we don't put unnecessary labels to the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And also, we don't talk about, okay, this is because of your father's trauma, this is because of your mother's trauma. We let the client realize it and speak.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? We don't push our understanding on the client, and neither, because then the client will start
Dr. Karan Mittal: analyzing the father from that perspective, even now. So we try to avoid very strong and sticky labels on any, any of the assets, on the client surface. And projection is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, projection bias also happens very commonly. We try to project our issues, or whatever we have gone through on the client's problems. So, I had this… so suppose I'm giving a very, very extreme example. If the therapist has undergone abuse in his childhood, and he
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, he kind of… a client comes who has also undergone abuse, then somewhere or the other, the therapist will start projecting the way he dealt with the abuse, the way… the emotions he has, the problem he has right now, on the client. And sometimes this becomes…
Dr. Karan Mittal: too much for the client to handle, because both of them have sailed in different boats. So we try avoiding our… try, you know, avoiding our experiences, whether it's devotional experiences, spiritual experiences, traumatic experiences, on the client. That's why, in psychology also, how much of personal information to share with the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's again a thing of taboo. Nowadays, people are opening up, but until a few years ago, therapists
Dr. Karan Mittal: never shared his personal things with the gift. So that's about the projection bias. So, why are we dealing with these biases? It's because
Dr. Karan Mittal: Next time when you are dealing with a counselor of yours, and you have completed your session, you have completed a few sessions, come back home, take, you know, reflect for 15 minutes, and see which advice came from a bias.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Which analysis came from a bias, which assumption came from a bias, and which was you kind of listening non-judgmentally, and then probably analyzing the client, or being empathetic to client, and then advising.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's why knowing your biases is equally important.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And countertransference bias, of course, again.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It happens in cases where you kind of transfer your issues, or your experiences, or something related in your life on the client. So, like, the example I've given, like, if you had a younger brother, and he's probably
Dr. Karan Mittal: are not talking to you, are not able to deal with him, take care of him, etc. And you kind of get a client who's of the same age, going through a similar issue, same looks, etc, who kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: feel that the client is your younger brother, and try projecting that feeling of the elder brother on the client. So that's a counter-transparent bias. Freud, Sigmund Freud spoke a lot about it, but not very important unless you are into clinical counseling. But just knowing that, are you projecting any of your issues
Dr. Karan Mittal: Relationships, any of your traumas, etc, on the client, plays an equal important role to become that empty container.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Juji.
Govind Das: So, therefore, every bias is fragmented until end.
Govind Das: I was just remembering, Wilderand was one who spent 50 years writing… History.
Govind Das: You know, wrote 13 volumes of history.
Govind Das: And the beauty in the introduction of his book, he explains.
Govind Das: Right? Imagine, you know, you spend all your life
Govind Das: like, there are certain historians in India
Govind Das: They're so arrogant about what they compiled, they want that to be the reference point.
Govind Das: No? Such a bias about their work.
Govind Das: But this man spent 50 years writing, and in the introduction, what does he mention?
Govind Das: He mentions that history Is nothing but imagination and prejudice.
Govind Das: And where does the prejudice arise from? Prejudice arises from my reference point.
Govind Das: And I will see the whole world based upon my reference point.
Govind Das: And what is my reference point? My reference point is nothing but my Anthak Karana.
Govind Das: Nope.
Govind Das: Confirmation diagnostic is Buddhi corrupted by Chitta.
Govind Das: means here, rather than, as I gave the example in one place, in one of the rooms.
Govind Das: It's very important to understand, somebody said, you know, Bhutti, how can Bhutti…
Govind Das: Because in the Bhagavad Gita, Sri Krishna explains.
Govind Das: I am the intelligence of the intelligent.
Govind Das: If you simply focus on reflecting your Buddhi, it has the power to…
Govind Das: You know, transcend the chitta, and process the chitta, rather than corrupted by… That's it.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: Then the cultural bias, cultural moral.
Govind Das: Alright, what does the Hankara do? Ahankara has an identity superiority complex.
Govind Das: And judging everybody. One of the reasons people go… don't go to spiritualist is…
Govind Das: The spiritualists deal with the details, rather than dealing with the essence.
Govind Das: I remember talking to an elderly, extremely traditional scholar.
Govind Das: but extremely sensitive in regards to what was happening. He said one of the reasons why our young people do not come to
Govind Das: The cultural activities, because they are judged by their dress, They're judged by their language.
Govind Das: They are judged by their, you know, their own generation.
Govind Das: Whether it is about sitting, whether it is their dress, whether it is their, you know, certain habits.
Govind Das: So what does it do? That Ahankara of a therapist, whether it is a spiritual or somebody else.
Govind Das: Gives them the authority, you cannot be doing things.
Govind Das: You can explain the next one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: No, no, the toolkit of this, how do we look at this? So, supposedly, I believe that I'm a very good devotee. I follow all my
Dr. Karan Mittal: things accordingly. So, the exercises I gave you now will start helping it out, helping over here. So, now if I feel that I'm very good at this particular thing, automatically have to be more aware that, for me, the cultural or the moral bias can be very strong.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because I feel, that's my ahangara speaking, that I'm very good at it. Now, on face.
Dr. Karan Mittal: value, we might say, no, no, like, you know, I'm not good, etc, etc. But there is where you need to kind of introspect and see that if internally you have this anankara of being right and, you know, super moral, etc, you might start imposing that particular cultural or moral bias on your chemistry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And supposedly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If I'm really intelligent, okay, and my IQ is probably higher compared to the client sitting in front of me, then the confirmation and the diagnostic bias will take over. Because I will feel clienti, client doesn't know anything, okay? My buddy has analyzed this.
Dr. Karan Mittal: this is my diagnosis, this is how it should work, and then I will start imposing that on the client. So my confirmation is already… has kind of, you know, concretized over here, that this client is particularly having a problem because he has this particular issue.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then, I will just keep on imposing that particular thing. So the exercise we did on Tuesday and Thursday will help you understand where is your dominance.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And if chitta, or your childhood experiences, or your conditionings, or your traumas are dominant for you, and you have many vast sanskaras
Dr. Karan Mittal: Kind of that are unexplored, and you yourself don't know how are they operating within you, then you will be seeing the client from the projection and counter-transparents perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So then, what we need to do is, we need to first work on ourselves, work on the roots of the sanskaras, work on the self-work. When you're doing a therapy or something, being supervised by someone who's more experienced into it, otherwise you will start projecting your sanskaras on the day. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Knowing which of the antercurrent is dominant for you will help you understand which bias you are more prone to.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And which bias you might impose on the client. So that's how you start working in this… working with the cells. And once you're one of those four undercurrents are sorted, then you are in much better as an empty container to understand the client's biases and…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's… that's how you integrate the Rishivaram… the Rishi's view of Antakarana for your self-work into your practice, yeah.
Govind Das: Therefore, Therefore, the certain, certain healing process, you know, like in the… in the prani killing.
Govind Das: After they've done with the client session, they cleanse themselves.
Govind Das: No, the therapist has to cleanse herself or himself so that the impressions do not carry forward.
Govind Das: Therefore, we have Nadith Plan, you know, we have…
Govind Das: In the Bhartiyadarshti kon, there is… there is a Snar, which… Tirtustan, right, Mantrasthan, so that
Govind Das: as Karanji mentioned, emptying with all the impressions, so that
Govind Das: You are able to process their information and give them right counsel.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think, like a doctor.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is also prone to infectious diseases and needs to take the precautions. Similarly, the therapist also has to continuously undergo that self-work. As I said in the first session also, there are so many therapies nowadays that mandate having 10, 12 sessions for the therapist with the senior therapist, to continue practicing that particular form of therapy, because over the years, they have realized that how much of
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, biases and accumulation of traumas, etc. happens. So, the therapist healed thyself. It's now the… now the new, new, technique of becoming a good therapist.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, we'll again get into a bias-based exercise. Now this exercise is a bit…
Dr. Karan Mittal: a bit more complicated, and that's why I'll take some time to explain it. So, we'll have 3 people.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The observer, the therapist, and the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, the client will bring something very, very… don't pick up something intense, or maybe continue with… with the same thing that you did in the previous exercise. And now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: take turns to become the therapist observable. Like, I saw one group, they were self-contemplating. Self-contemplation as just a limit, okay? We have been seeing that situation for years. But when the therapist asks questions, probably you'll go one or two steps deeper. So, don't… don't let go of that opportunity. Someone acts as a therapist.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And now, therapists ask questions to that particular issue that the client is
Dr. Karan Mittal: talking about, okay? And probably might also give some, have you tried this, have you tried that? And now, in this whole exercise, the role of observer becomes very important. The observer first keeps a watch.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, like, like, sees, like, in one of the groups didn't finish it. So the observer will time the session for 7 minutes, that round for 7 minutes, and the observer will try to analyze if the therapist is coming from a bias, okay? Is coming from a bias. So, like, in one of the sessions,
Dr. Karan Mittal: one of the groups I went, all three were saying that, okay, this is the same problem with me, because my family is like this, someone was saying my employers are like this, someone was saying my father is like this. The therapist was projecting his issue on the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's… that's projection bias.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? The therapist is already analyzing the situation of the client based on his experience with his father, or with his boss, etc. So the observer now becomes mindful, and at the end of the 7 minutes, in 30 seconds, gives a summary that probably these were the biases that you observed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And we end it over there. We don't get into discussion this time, no unnecessary discussion. Stick to the process, and these are the… then you'll get strong takeaways from the project.
Dr. Karan Mittal: A process. So, 30 seconds to 1 minute of debrief, where observer shares, and the therapist want to play, so that's possible. This could be one of the biases, etc, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I hope the exercise is clear, Project. Should we…
Rutuja Nayak: Dr. Gardan, is it possible, for us to regroup with the same, with same people, so that it's easier for the time limit to discuss, to continue the discussion?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I can try that, because then I'll require the… I don't remember who was there in which group, and I'll have to create the breakout groups manually then. Now, Zoom does it automatically, it might push people here and there. So, maybe from next time we can… I can do that manually, I think. But today, I cannot.
Dr. Karan Mittal: commit that, yeah, because I don't remember.
Rutuja Nayak: Because of the time limit earlier, only.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I remember that's what I…
Govind Das: If they don't mind… if they don't mind, without going into the room, can we do it here only, if people don't mind?
Govind Das: If people want to play that role in the group itself.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yeah, if anyone wants to take up a role of a client and a therapist, we can do two rounds, probably, and all of us being observers, that could be done. Yeah, that would be a good exercise, in fact.
Govind Das: everywhere.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Someone can volunteer, yeah.
Rutuja Nayak: Yeah.
Rutuja Nayak: Are they?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So if anyone wants to volunteer, that would be great.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I don't know, yeah.
Rutuja Nayak: Yeah.
Rutuja Nayak: Okay, I don't mind going, to be a client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: client. Anyone who would like to volunteer as a therapist?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: everything.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, when we do trainings, we train with 50-100 people, and still we volunteer, so it's a safe space, and we are not taking some major issues, so please go ahead. We all will be observant of our own biases.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Lavinachi, would you like to try? Sorry, I had to pick up a name, so…
Lavina Shewaramani: Yeah, I will try to be a therapist.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah. So, so, so, Prutujaji and Lavin Naji, you can take.
Govind Das: Everybody else is obsole.
Govind Das: Huh.
Dr. Karan Mittal: All of us are on Zoomers, yes.
Govind Das: We can choose one of them, we can represent, you know, rather than…
Govind Das: Everybody commenting, one or two people can comment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so… Litag and RTG work in the observers, I guess, yeah?
Dr. Karan Mittal: For now. I have to pick up because no one is volunteering.
Lavina Shewaramani: It also helps me as a therapist, you know, one of your sirs, you all can also help me, you know, so I will also get some, you know, support.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sure. I just can switch off their, videos, let them have their space, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Bluetooth Jajiv, please.
Rutuja Nayak: So, I have this tendency of, controlling things in my, way, not, out of dominance, but out of the fear
Rutuja Nayak: or out of protecting. So, specifically talking about my sister, picking up my sister over here, I have this tendency to be very over-possessive and protective for her, and because of this, I tend to, you know, put my, restrictions on her, in terms of don't do this, do it like it way. So, I want things to be done
Rutuja Nayak: In a controlled manner, just… but out of… the intention is to protect, not to dominate, or be like that. So that's… that's my… that's the problem.
Rutuja Nayak: that,
Rutuja Nayak: I am dealing with. I mean, I'm working on it. I do realize that it's her own life, it's her own individual identity, and I have to let her be and let her experience, things, but, earlier I used to be very impulsive, in terms of reacting if she would be late at home, or,
Rutuja Nayak: doing things other way, but now I've… the intensity has lowered, but it still exists. So, just quoting a example with a sister, but other than this, if I'm close to someone, I have this tendency to have this ownership kind of a thing.
Rutuja Nayak: But again, with an intention of protectiveness and not dominance, so yeah.
Lavina Shewaramani: Since how long are you, having this kind of nature?
Lavina Shewaramani: Like, since how long you're having this kind of nature.
Rutuja Nayak: Oh, sick.
Lavina Shewaramani: How is the reaction of the people whom you do this with?
Rutuja Nayak: mostly it's sister, so she's mostly concerned, whenever I do this, because she's like, you see, you don't have to worry, I'll take care of myself, because eventually, if something happens to me, you will get affected a lot.
Rutuja Nayak: So, she's more worried than irritated, I would say, for me.
Rutuja Nayak: And, so this, so just to… I think I'll have to share this, I lost my parents at a very early age, I was 20 years old, and then I started… I completed my graduation and started earning, so me and my sister, we stay alone. She's 3 years younger to me. So, eventually, the sense of ownership came from then, you know, I have to be now, the…
Rutuja Nayak: member who would, you know, take care of things and people, and have to do everything on my own. So, I think that came out of cell hyper-independence also.
Rutuja Nayak: So, yeah.
Lavina Shewaramani: You have this moral that parents always are caretakers, you know, they were taking care of us, and then that responsibilities come on you right now.
Lavina Shewaramani: So you feel that something? Like, responsibility?
Rutuja Nayak: Oh…
Rutuja Nayak: I would not say responsibility, I was always very close to my sister, since childhood. Like, I always had this motherly feeling for her. It was never taught to me, it was just there, existed. But yeah, when my father passed away, I did have this feeling, you know, I have to now take the charge of the family, I have to look after my mother and my sister, I have to protect
Rutuja Nayak: them, no one can say or, you know, point out to them in terms of anything. Because I felt that, you know, though these two people, my mother and my sister, they both are very
Rutuja Nayak: emotionally sensitive people, they can be manipulated easily, they… they can trust anyone easily. So…
Rutuja Nayak: I feel… then I felt, you know, there should be someone who can be a bit logical than emotional. I am emotional myself, I am, but,
Rutuja Nayak: I don't trust people easily. I take my time, I take my experiences, so that's where it came from, actually.
Rutuja Nayak: This behavior of mine.
Lavina Shewaramani: Like, it's only with your mother and sister, or you do your natures like that? Like, is your nature that way?
Rutuja Nayak: It's not there now, it's just my sister now, yeah.
Lavina Shewaramani: Yeah, so it's only with your sister, or you do it with other people also, whom you said you're close to, you do them. So is it with your other family members, and you know your friends' family?
Rutuja Nayak: See, with others, I do not have someone, as of now, who I can, put this kind of restrictions. I would say. I don't have a partner or anything like that. But, as of now, it's my sister with whom I tend to, you know, be like that.
Rutuja Nayak: For now, yeah.
Rutuja Nayak: But I'm worried. I may carry forward it, and there's a tendency to do that with my children or with my partner because of this behavior. So, I'm aware and…
Rutuja Nayak: trying to… Figure it out, how to work on this.
Lavina Shewaramani: So basically, these are your morals, like, you need to… so be protective, and you know, you need, you know, you need to safeguard your own people.
Lavina Shewaramani: And those are your morals. You believe that this is part of your moral? Where does it come from? I'm trying to understand. Is it your moral, or is it that you believe that it is, you know, your duty, or, you know, how it is? Like, how do you feel when you do this to your… whoever you, like, your family? What do you feel in your mind?
Rutuja Nayak: It's absolutely out of love, I mean, there's no, morality or responsibility as such.
Rutuja Nayak: Kuchina, yes, I don't have a thought like that, but it's…
Rutuja Nayak: Just out of love to be protected, Maybe, or… I…
Rutuja Nayak: That's the only way I can think of.
Lavina Shewaramani: What if they don't listen to you? I mean, there must be time when the people don't listen to you. Like, how would you react then? I mean…
Lavina Shewaramani: If your sister doesn't listen to you, you are protecting her, but she takes it in the wrong way, and she reacts, and she doesn't… how do you react then?
Rutuja Nayak: I feel bad, about it, and I was like, why she don't understand where I'm coming from? I don't want her to get hurt, or, you know, to be in a problem or situation, so I might get hurt.
Rutuja Nayak: Is what I would say. Oh, sometimes I might react angrily also, ki, you know…
Rutuja Nayak: It has to be in a certain way. But then, yeah, I do, realize it later that
Rutuja Nayak: you have to be things to flow. I mean, in terms of… because we both are two different individuals, and I have…
Rutuja Nayak: I have to let her be her. But, yeah, but the… the reactions do come. The response takes time to be processed.
Lavina Shewaramani: Are you valued for it? I mean, do people… I mean, your close people value for you this kind of nature, like…
Lavina Shewaramani: You are valued, like, you know, like, you take care of them, and you are, you know, thinking good for them. Do they value that, or you are ignored? Like, I mean, you know, like, that's your nature.
Rutuja Nayak: No, no, they do value, SRNA. They do value and respect.
Rutuja Nayak: See, because they know I'm not, here to, again.
Rutuja Nayak: as I've mentioned earlier, also, out… there is… nothing out of dominance or out of this sense of superiority or anything. It's just out of…
Rutuja Nayak: Protecting them, is what I feel.
Rutuja Nayak: Security, the sense of security is…
Rutuja Nayak: Yeah, that's what I tend to see.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think we'll stop here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, RTG, and who else was the observer? Could you notice any bias?
Aarti Ganesh: Probably, more or less, I think Lavinachi did a really wonderful job.
Dr. Karan Mittal: leaves.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's… she did a lot of consequences.
Aarti Ganesh: Yes.
Aarti Ganesh: Perhaps a tinge of cultural bias, maybe? I mean, I… My, understanding is right.
Aarti Ganesh: The question about how…
Aarti Ganesh: she, I mean, Sutujaji being the elder sibling, and it is expected that the elder sibling takes, care of the younger one, perhaps that.
Aarti Ganesh: A tinge of it may have, come in.
Aarti Ganesh: It's what I've learned.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of course, Levinergy does not to point out that it was a short duration, and we cannot diagnose it so early, but also a bit of projection in the end, where you said, do people value, somewhere kind of reflecting maybe a belief of yours?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it… of course, but it… it had to mature too quickly for us to put it as a bias in you. You had to kind of ask in a limited time frame. Yes, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, I think both the biases somewhere. Maybe what I could also do is, maybe if we get… if someone volunteers as a client, I'll become the therapist, and I would a bit dramatically show the biases how it works, so that you all can pick it up much…
Dr. Karan Mittal: quicker and faster, I think. So, if anyone wants to volunteer as a client, I might try to kind of demonstrate two or three biases.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Any one of you?
jithendra myla: Yeah, I can be a client.
jithendra myla: Beautiful.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you.
jithendra myla: Yeah, one, one of the issues I face…
jithendra myla: is with my brother-in-laws. I have 3 sisters and 3 brother-in-laws.
jithendra myla: Oh… So, basically, it's a… You know, we… It usually…
jithendra myla: our culture is… a lot of times, people don't talk, but it's highly influenced by the movies. So, in Telugu, in Andhrak, a lot of Telugu movies, they project
jithendra myla: Oh… the brother-in-law has to help the brother, like, my… I have to help my sister's husband
jithendra myla: Heavily, into, like, in each, every moment of the celebration, like, in…
jithendra myla: It could be a birthday party, or it could be their daughter's,
jithendra myla: the, the college ceremonies, or… it could be anything. The expectation is, like, you have to be there at least 4-5 days advance, and then help him in every nitty-gritty stuff. And then if you're… my…
jithendra myla: My mind is, like, I'm in… I've grown up in hostel, stayed away from my family most of my life.
jithendra myla: My mind is geared, like, always individual thinking, and my priorities are my family, kids, and then my mom.
jithendra myla: And my father passed away. So my responsibilities is not to take care of my sisters after they get married. But the,
jithendra myla: But the culture is, like, in different families.
jithendra myla: The sons still help the brother-in-laws, the sisters, after they get married.
jithendra myla: So, when you don't help, the reflection comes in a different way. They get angry on you a lot of times.
jithendra myla: I…
Dr. Karan Mittal: But what's wrong with helping Jitindraji?
jithendra myla: You know, the problem is…
jithendra myla: out of… if you are ambitious, like, you know, I… I work, and then I do, other services, like running my own art gallery, and then,
jithendra myla: you know, when the kids are… they have so many things, the kids, programs, and then you take care of your mom, and on top of everything, you have your own spiritual practices. They take up a lot of your time, like, my spiritual practices take up, like.
jithendra myla: 2 to 3 hours a day. And you don't have time to spend with your extended family
jithendra myla: I mean, you can go…
jithendra myla: Once in a year, or if you… you can go there when they're admitted in hospital, or help them out.
jithendra myla: But you cannot… you know.
jithendra myla: All these birthday parties, they are, like, they are, like, meaningless to me. Even I don't celebrate my own birthday or my kid's birthday.
jithendra myla: And The birthday parties, it could be a lot of things, you know.
jithendra myla: You know, Sankranthi, Deepali, You know, for…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is it stressful for you, or it's irritating for you?
jithendra myla: It's, well, it's not in my… Oh…
jithendra myla: circle of things that I want to do.
jithendra myla: it's not stressful, or it… I mean, it's… when I go there, I feel happy, you know, when you go to the extended family, you meet your sisters, your cousins, your nieces, everyone. You feel happy, you spend a lot of time, but…
jithendra myla: When you're ambitious, you want to do a lot of… you want to accomplish a lot of things within this lifetime. You don't get time to spend with your extended family.
jithendra myla: I mean, I'm there only for if they are in trouble. I'm not there to,
jithendra myla: To, you know, spend my quality time with, chit-chatting, or…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hold on.
jithendra myla: I mean, helping… And also, you know, you have to… Oh…
jithendra myla: offer clothes, you have to… like, every sankranthi or every festival, you have to buy the clothes, you have to exchange a lot of gifts and trades. These are all silly things which you don't… you're not believed in, and then you just avoid it, and then the return that you get is…
jithendra myla: They observe that you're, ignoring them, and then they will try to get angry on you, and then my reflection is, like, I don't… I stop talking for years to them.
jithendra myla: No.
jithendra myla: So that's the situation, and then… so that… how do you… how do you deal with that situation?
Dr. Karan Mittal: So you are saying that you are ambitious, and that's why you have your other practices, social practices, and that's why you don't have bandwidth for these people?
jithendra myla: Yes.
jithendra myla: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But how difficult it is to manage?
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, so many… like, it's… like, how difficult it is to manage? Because I also, probably, I manage my studies also, I manage my classes, sessions, so how difficult it is for you to kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably manage these things together. Like, I have my spiritual practices also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'm making it dramatic, but just be observant here.
jithendra myla: How hard?
jithendra myla: Well… It's a waste of time, like, if they are not… devotees, then, you know.
jithendra myla: I have to eat honey and garlic when I go there.
jithendra myla: And then I have to watch movies, and then it's like, whole day, it's just chit-chat, nothing there.
jithendra myla: So… I enjoy it in one way, but it's still, it's… it's not…
jithendra myla: Something I want to do.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes, so I'll stop over here, Jitinji, and I'm really thankful to you to kind of come up and share that example. Of course, I'll talk to you on WhatsApp individually about this whole thing, but just for giving the example, how many biases all of you noticed? I gave 3 clear-cut dramatic biases, and of course, very abruptly, so that
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's… it's… you can observe it enough. Yes, Levi Naji.
Lavina Shewaramani: projection bias.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Protection bias was there, very strongly, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Vyansha Khal, yes.
DhyanShala: Cultural West.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Cultural bias, okay, okay. What else?
Dr. Karan Mittal: I also did a diagnostic bias. Before he could complete it, I said, ambition and this and that, you know, I mixed it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: For him, right? So I did 3 biases together over here, different, different 3 biases. And also, if you see, over the whatever 5 minutes we did, we came to the root of the problem also. So the questioning happened in a way where he said, interacting with devotees
Dr. Karan Mittal: non-devotees, and I have to break my rules. So it's not about bandwidth, it's like… I'm sorry, Exitandaji, I'm just taking a bit of liberty over here. So it's not just about the bandwidth he has, it's also about the cultural bias he has, that, you know, non-devotees interaction, and then eating onion-garlic, moral bias, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, this is how biases start projecting. Because I started feeling already, I'm also managing so many things. What's the harm in managing so many relations? The root cause was…
Dr. Karan Mittal: interacting with knowledge. Rubji, would you like to add something? Sorry, I just took over it, because, yeah.
Govind Das: Yeah, very good. Jitendra went deeper, explained, and
Govind Das: You know, as you pointed out.
Govind Das: You know, imagine… imagine how much biases we operate from.
Govind Das: This was a simple… a small sample.
Govind Das: Even though it was a drama, but actually in real life, that is how we operate.
Govind Das: You know, the entire world is operating on the principle of this bias alone.
Govind Das: And it did come out naturally because there is a chitta, you know, knowledge is there.
Govind Das: But bias is stronger. Therefore, therefore, reconditioning
Govind Das: Becomes very important for the therapist, and also for the client.
Govind Das: And then, therefore, therefore the Bharti, the IKS, offers this option of the people ask this question, can we deal with our karma?
Govind Das: Is it possible to overcome our,
Govind Das: there is no free will. Like, even some of the modern scientist people believe that there is no free will. We are driven by our neurological, situation.
Govind Das: But Bhartia, which are Dara, Bhartia Knowledge Systems says no.
Govind Das: Yes, we know we have the past, but we can deal our biases and transcend our achitta.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Share the further slides.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, one of the homeworks that you all can take, Up is, no.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Whatever last few interactions you have had with your clients, family members.
Dr. Karan Mittal: counselees, etc. You could also, also start seeing from which bias you are analyzing which case. And probably.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If it's a Zoom session, then one of the easy things is getting a transcript and then reading what you are saying. If it's a… if it's an in-person session, we record the session audio-wise and then re-hear the session. So, self-work…
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's why it becomes important. Like, in many therapies, we have to record the audio and video of doing a few sample sessions, and send it to a trainer for them to analyze what's going wrong in our
Dr. Karan Mittal: session, or work with a supervisor. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, so… so that was the exercise.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'm sorry, I'll just give you a mute.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I could have also done the counter-transparents bias. I would have said that, oh, my father deals with family responsibilities also, and, you know, work also, and does this ad now also, but still he is able to manage what's the problem with you? So that also could be, like, one of the additional biases that I could have operated. If not the projection, then counter-transpirence usually takes over.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… so non-judgment is not niceness, you know, it's a technical skill that we all need to develop. And like Yog Sutra says, that yoga is Chittabritti nirodha. The more your Chittabrittis or your vasnas and sanskaras are settled, the better you are at yoga, and the better you come out as a therapist or a counselor.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, we're…
Govind Das: Oops.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Govind Das: Yep.
Govind Das: So where does this judgment come from?
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: again, in the… in the Indian culture, If we see…
Govind Das: We do not communicate with respect.
Govind Das: We believe that communication is not respectful. Father and son
Govind Das: They rarely communicate. Father speaks, son listens. Nowadays, son and daughter speak, and father listen.
Govind Das: Right? There is no communication, because we fear confrontation.
Govind Das: Take Arjuna's example. Arjuna was happy to beg, Rather than confront his grandfather.
Govind Das: Now, that was a physical confrontation where he has to shoot. Now, verbal shooting…
Govind Das: You know, verbal shooting happens when there is a reactive behavior.
Govind Das: But verbal discussion doesn't happen when we have to go deeper.
Govind Das: So, therefore, the judgment Whether it is whoever has the greater power, they make decisions, they do not discuss.
Govind Das: And it comes from that position that
Govind Das: An educated son will tell his father what to do.
Govind Das: And a growing son has to hear from the father what the son has to do.
Govind Das: It comes from the ahankara of positioning, whether father positioning, a spiritual therapist positioning, or a guru position.
Govind Das: Right.
Govind Das: So that is what the ahankara comes from. We can explain the fear on.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, also adding to Ankara, in transpersonal therapy, there is something called as law of dominance, you know?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Somewhere or the other, you need to have that domination over the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you don't have that dominance, the therapy won't work. But at the same time, you cannot prove yourself to always be the right one and the wise one in them.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that causes the problem. You cannot let go of the domination, because if you're not able to dominate the client enough, therapy won't work. But at the same time, you also have to be that container of
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably taking in what the client is saying, readjusting your, analysis, diagnosis, treatment. So that's when a thin control in this ego, ahankara, is needed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You cannot be too dominant, and you cannot be too light-off. So that's how we adjust the ego, and it comes with practice. It comes with understanding what went wrong with a particular client, etc. There, the ego comes in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So the slide is basically where the judgment… where do we judge from? So the right side is the biases thing. So, incomplete models of mind, where we… we have kind of made those black and white biases, that if this is this, then this is the problem, this could be the problem. So that's the right side, which will be dealt in much detail. And the second thing is fear.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So sometimes in the therapy, we need to let go of
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, like, now, now in the Dharma also, I was interrupting it, okay? So somewhere, you have to kind of, again, balance both the things. Also, being the container, and also, kind of, if the client is going in
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, in a verbosity, kind of speaking, speaking, speaking. So, kind of being that dominant one and stopping the client. So, you have to let go of different, different fears that you have about the therapy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: About doing wrong to the client, of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, sometimes you also need to accept that you were wrong in particular judgment, etc, and then need to rectify it. So, this… this fear of going wrong, or doing wrong, or the therapy going wrong, also needs to kind of be given up, else you will make decisions based on those fears. Okay, sometimes
Dr. Karan Mittal: many sessions, because the therapist is having this fear of not upsetting the client for money reasons, for losing a client reason, for if the client has some big personality, then you don't want to upset them. Sometimes we keep on taking
Dr. Karan Mittal: whatever the client is saying, the way it is, because we have this fear of losing any of these components. So sometimes you need to understand that you are operating from a fear, and you need to go and then, you know, stop a client there and there. So these are the things that you learn with practice. So, that's where judgment comes from.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I think we will stop here, and we can take questions from you. Yes.
Govind Das: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, okay. Any questions?
Dr. Karan Mittal: The…
Govind Das: sometimes here only.
Vikram Chakilam: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Hmm.
DhyanShala: Tamji, please, please go. Please go ahead.
Vikram Chakilam: So, I was able to sense the biases, but not able to categorize them, so I want to learn more about the biases so that I can work on myself. Can you please suggest some reading?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, we, I will… I will send… when we… I give you the notes of the two days combined, there would be some techniques to work on each of the biases.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And towards the end of the session, in 5 minutes, we'll… one sanskara that you picked up in the first round, we'll work on that sanskara also. I'll guide a group meditation, where we work on that particular sanskara, like a 5-minute thing that will give you a clue of how to work on samskara. Since someone asked me about
Dr. Karan Mittal: how to work on a particular sense, Carl? Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Shubamji? Yes.
DhyanShala: I have, it was a very, very interesting session today. One little reflection and extending question from them.
DhyanShala: From the discussion that we had today,
DhyanShala: In the form of two clients, a two distinguished members of us, our team, has shown that
DhyanShala: So I just conclude… no, it's not a conclusion, I just feel that living beings are just a storehouse of some scars.
DhyanShala: We all have faced so many things, so many ups and downs.
DhyanShala: Something had gone adverse to us, something had gone… had gone favorable to us. We thought that this could have been… happened in different way, but happened in different way, not in our way. So, these all are making some sense cause to us.
DhyanShala: And this is how our belief system is growing up.
DhyanShala: understanding, or… Motivate… or just conditioning our anthakaran, and finally making our personality.
DhyanShala: So, the main thing is Tanskar.
DhyanShala: The question arises how we can settle our Santqar.
DhyanShala: So, as per my understanding, my reading, it is, definitely there are many panchiklesh in yog, Darshan, we talk about Panchikesh.
DhyanShala: We talk about shed repo. So these all are kind of, this all are aggravated through some scar only.
DhyanShala: So, its weapon which can counter this is definitely Yam and Yam.
DhyanShala: And apart from that, definitely there are shardsambhati we have.
DhyanShala: Chitty Prasadam we have. So this can be the way… Through that, we can…
DhyanShala: settle over some spar, or also through Nishkam Bhau and Anasakt.
DhyanShala: Tendency.
DhyanShala: or something more you can add in it. This is what I understand. This is what I am able to digest till now, after my reading.
Dr. Karan Mittal: business.
DhyanShala: Yep.
Govind Das: Yes, Afghanamagulia. Where is this? Your name is…
DhyanShala: Hurom Singh.
Govind Das: See, the… whatever you explained about the… the solution, They're… they are… very impactful.
Govind Das: Okay.
Govind Das: But our, our problem is, therefore, Indian knowledge system is very equipped in regards to giving solutions.
Govind Das: But what is the problem is the language what the modern people require.
Govind Das: Right?
Govind Das: The same thing, how do you process and make it more digestible?
Govind Das: Generally, what happens, if you study now carefully.
Govind Das: Like, when we talk about shared reports, Right.
Govind Das: So people feel, oh my god, that means we can't exist only, because it's talking about overcoming
Govind Das: Pleasure also. Overcoming controlled anger also.
Govind Das: So what has happened in our system in Bahartir, which are Dara, even some of our politicians, those who studied socialism, they said Indian system speaks a lot of pessimism.
Govind Das: Giving up everything.
Govind Das: Right. So therefore, the same, whatever you explained, how do I make it more feasible?
Govind Das: So that people can understand and implement. Like I was discussing with one friend.
Govind Das: We discuss mostly about moksha and Dharma.
Govind Das: We do not discuss about karma and Artha.
Govind Das: In the Mahabharat, when I told somebody.
Govind Das: Lakshmi Devi was asked by Rukmini.
Govind Das: Rukmini asked Lakshmi Devi, Ki, where do you reside?
Govind Das: Lakshmi means… resources also, Lakshmiens, you know, wealth also.
Govind Das: Now, Lakshmi answered to Rukmini, Wherever people are satisfied, I do not reside there.
Govind Das: So I told this to one businessman, he said, how, how, you know, it's, it's, it's contradictory. He said, earning money is greed, and we have to, we have to actually stop this greed.
Govind Das: So, what we do, we mostly focus on Dharma and moksha, and Dharmic artha and Dharmic karma is undermined or slandered.
Govind Das: Right, so therefore, whatever solution is spoke about is what the solution has to be offered, but in a language
Govind Das: and more integrated. So, Dharma is there, Artha is there, karma is there, and moksha is the consequences of Dharma and Artha and karma.
Govind Das: And we're going to discuss this one in our future slides, where to integrate.
Govind Das: You know, so therefore, yes, the solutions, whatever you explained, are impactful, but they are not accepted by our own people only, unfortunately.
Govind Das: Next generation people say, hey, you're redundant, you know, you don't make sense on it.
Govind Das: And therefore, modern psychology, if you see.
Govind Das: You know, he has taken a lot of volume, used a lot of Indian concept.
Govind Das: But the way he presented was much more feasible, much more understandable, and that became part of modern professional psychologists.
Govind Das: Which has not happened with our own system.
DhyanShala: Guruji, Carl Jung also used, as per my understanding, what I have read, Carl Jung also utilized this Mandel color, mandal art.
Govind Das: Very good, yeah, very much.
DhyanShala: Am I right? Yes.
Govind Das: Very much, very much, yeah.
Govind Das: Yes, Karan, you want to add something?
Dr. Karan Mittal: No, Brujay, I think… I think, like you said, Chick Prasad, etc, that's happiness, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and also probably not becoming Shunya and all that indifference. All these are now getting included in therapy in more consumable chunks, as Proji mentioned. So it's easier to start from there, and then probably take it further.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's how it is. Top-down or bottom-top approach, there's a difference. I think that's the whole thing. Yeah, that's my understanding. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, Geetrajim?
Geeta Khoosal: Prabho, going back to biases, I just want to know, what is the line between empathy and projection?
Govind Das: Well, we're not… Currently answered.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yeah, so I think the easiest way that I kind of differentiate between both is
Dr. Karan Mittal: if I'm saying something to the client, or if I'm analyzing the client, like I said.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, that PhD and my studies and everything. Is that part helping the client?
Dr. Karan Mittal: If it's not helping the client, it's making things worse for him, then I'm projecting something out here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But if it is helping the client, some example from my life is helping the client in a way, then I'm empathizing with the client. And that changes from client to client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Same client might react positively, as I said in one of the sessions, same client might react positively to the concept of God, and same client might react negatively, because he's not able to follow the principles or the practices.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So empathy and projection keeps on changing from client. So that you need to titrate based on working, like, one or two, three sessions with clients, give you an idea what works for the client.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Beautiful.
Govind Das: Just like in the Mahabharat, very, very interesting example, when the Ropadhi
Govind Das: she actually meets with Krishna after the attempted disrobing. I hope everybody knows this story. You know, she was attempted to be disrupted by the Kurus, and eventually
Govind Das: Pandavas came to the forest, And she meets with Krishna.
Govind Das: And the report is an outburst.
Govind Das: You know, questioning Krishna why he did not come and protect her.
Govind Das: And if you study the way Krishna spoke, he did not tell her karma theory.
Govind Das: He did not speak to her, oh, you did this, therefore you're receiving this. He didn't speak to her that.
Govind Das: He didn't remind her, I gave you so much of sorry.
Govind Das: You know, how ungrateful you are. He didn't say that.
Govind Das: He just heard Dropadi, and he said, whoever has done this to you, I will teach them lesson.
Govind Das: And Rapadi starts crying.
Govind Das: All the truth of providing her sari was not reminded to her.
Govind Das: Karma theory was not spoken to her.
Govind Das: Krishna empathized by saying, I will take action against them.
Govind Das: Right? So… So it's… that is the distinction. You know, if somebody needs to hear karma theory.
Govind Das: And it is going to benefit
Govind Das: I'll use my own mother's example. She lost both her daughters.
Govind Das: You know, one daughter she lost when she was 30-year-old, another daughter she just lost 2 years ago. A mother losing both her daughters.
Govind Das: Very painful. And she asked this question to me, why this happened to me?
Govind Das: And why God did this to me.
Govind Das: Only two questions she asked.
Govind Das: And my answer was, you know what, the world is designed like that.
Govind Das: You know, death… the question of death cannot be asked only, because it is part of life.
Govind Das: There is no explanation.
Govind Das: Am I right?
Govind Das: I said, I could have told, what can you do, you know, she's a spiritual practitioner, or this is Krishna's test, this is God's mercy, you know, that's something…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Here's all that stuff.
Govind Das: Right? So, and the second one is, I said.
Govind Das: It has nothing to do with your karma, that is how it functions.
Govind Das: And Krishna, because she worships Krishna.
Govind Das: He will not try to test you to see how sincere a devotee you are, because
Govind Das: God does not put people in test by taking somebody away from them to prove their credibility.
Govind Das: This is a very rare example. So, after saying this, she's never, ever raised question again in her life. You know, I meet her regularly. She lost her second daughter 3 years ago. After that, she's never raised that question.
Govind Das: So it's important, when you speak, what you speak, as Karan said, it is benefiting
Govind Das: Then, that is empathy. It is…
Govind Das: Causing, counterproductive, then it is projection.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, Ruji, I think in Mahabharat, also, I think Krishna empathizes first with Yudhishtar, and then later chastises him for that match, right, Ruji? So, same person, different…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, kind of interventions at different times work different. So all this comes up, like, it… you need to develop it, and it comes up, like, as a skill later. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ruthu Jaji, and then we can start with…
Rutuja Nayak: So my question is, there's this statement that was in this PDF which said, body reacts based on past impression. What does it exactly mean, and how do we identify if it's a recent past example, or if it's something of past life?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Soon?
Dr. Karan Mittal: The way I use it in my clinical practice is we don't open up Pandora's box unless it's needed.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So if it's a past life, or some past life thing, we don't get into that realm unless it is warranted. Like, we have done everything of this life light right up until the childhood of working on that sanskara or vasana. If that has also not resolved what issue we are dealing with.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then we go to the past life. So past life is approached more like a clinical thing, rather than something that, okay, this is related to past life, open a past life, close it, and then this will be solved. So… so we don't…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Kind of label it to a past life, unless we have tried everything of this.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That makes it clinical, that keeps the therapist in check, that we're not imposing a past life regression or something on every second client that we are getting. So it keeps a check. It's a clinical check on your skills. Otherwise, it's easy for everyone to create a story, okay, I died because of hunger in this whole life, and that's why I have acidity in this. It's an easy metaphor.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So, so we keep it to this life first, stress, etc, and then take it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: To that year.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Flags.
Govind Das: Sometimes the astrologer will also tell you, oh, this is because of your,
Govind Das: Pitra Dosh, or Matri Dosh, right? You know, making a blanket statement so that, you know, you are…
Govind Das: impacted by that. So that's very important to see, past as past.
Govind Das: And rather than getting into very deeper analysis, because if the past
Govind Das: Is understood, which past doesn't matter, and we have the solution to deal with the past.
Govind Das: Then you move forward.
Rutuja Nayak: I don't.
Govind Das: Yeah.
Govind Das: Okay, we'll stop here, and any questions or anything is there, you please can also post it on the… on the group.
Govind Das: Vice or words.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, just one more thing. That sanskara exercise, tomorrow will begin with that 5-minute exercise. So my request to you as a homework is, pick up that Sanskara you took up in the first practice, and then get to the second question. Where did you hear it from? Parent, teacher, relatives, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Get to the second question, just contemplate a bit, and then tomorrow's exercise would be beneficial to you. You can change the sanskar also if you don't get the answer to the second question, but pick up a strong association that I heard this from my father, my teacher, my grandfather, whatever it is, yeah, and how it is impacting you today.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And we'll do one transpersonal exercise tomorrow to resolve.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yep.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Okay. Thank you, everyone.
Rutuja Nayak: Thank you.